Everybody, today's דף Daf is ט"ז, Tet-Zayin, 16. We pick up on
ט"ו עמוד ב', Tet-Vav Amud Bet, and we're in the middle of
the story of אלישע Elisha slash
אחר, Acher, אלישע בן אבויה. Elisha ben Abuyah. And the last section
of this story is going to deal with the issues about רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir allowing himself to learn
from אלישע בן אבויה. Elisha ben Abuyah. We just had the whole
fascinating discussion about saving him from גיהנום Gehennom and presumably bringing him
into גן עדן, Gan Eden, which shows that interesting ambivalence, you know,
and conflictual feelings or attitudes towards him. And now we pick up
with the following: בתו של אחר. Bito shel Acher. It is about
ten lines down in the medium-sized lines. בתו של אחר אתיא לקמיה
דרבי. Bito shel Acher atya l'kamei d'Rabbi. So she came to רבי,
Rabbi, because רבי Rabbi was the next generation, right? אחר Acher was
a contemporary of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אמרה ליה, Amrah lei, she
said to him, רבי פרנסני, Rabbi parneseini, sustain me, like, you know,
needed food. So here you have אחר's Acher's children, daughter, you know,
it doesn't have any, you know, anything to support herself on, which
raises interesting questions, right? Which is, did he provide for her? If
אחר Acher went and, you know, was engaged in the, you know,
a hedonistic lifestyle, what does he, you
know—what? Exactly. And if, exactly. And you know, so it raises interesting
questions, like is there a subtext here that he completely, you know,
followed a hedonistic lifestyle and abandoned his family? Because again, you know,
the question about his sort of moral character other than that bizarre
story about him cutting up that child, you know, usually isn't so
much in question. Anyway, so אמר לה, Amar lah, so רבי Rabbi
said to her, בתי, Biti, line starts with אמר לה, Amar lah,
בתי, Biti, my daughter, מי את? Mi at? Who are you? He
didn't know who this woman was. So אמרה ליה, Amrah lei, she
said to him, בתו של אחר אני, Bito shel Acher ani, I'm
the daughter of אחר, Acher, she might have said, אלישע בן אבויה.
Elisha ben Abuyah. Okay. אמר לה, Amar lah, he said to her,
עדיין יש מזרעו בעולם? Adayin yesh mizaro ba'olam? What, is his seed,
his descendants, still around? והכתיב, V'haktiv, the verse says, לא נין לו
ולא נכד בעמו, Lo nin lo velo neched be'amo, not a child
or a grandchild to him and, you know, not a grandchild among
his nation, ואין שריד במגוריו, V'ein sarid bimgoorav, and there'll be no
remnant, you know, in his dwelling place. So if he was a
רשע, rasha, how could it be that he still has a remnant
in this world, children in this world? אמרה ליה, Amrah lei, she
said to him, זכור לתורתו ואל תזכור מעשיו. Zechor l'Torato v'al tizkor
ma'asav. Remember his Torah, don't remember his deeds afterwards. מיד ירדה אש
וסכסכה ספסלו של רבי. Miyad yardah esh v'sichsechah safsalo shel Rabbi.
And immediately a fire descended and it singed the chair of רבי.
Rabbi. בכה ואמר, רבי Bakha v'amar Rabbi, cried and said, בכה ואמר
Bakha v'amar, רבי, Rabbi רבי Rabbi cried and said, ומה למתגנין בה
כך, Umah l'misganin bah kach,
imagine those that denigrate Torah, you know, that this in the—that they
are so meritorious that, you know, this fire comes down to show,
you know, how careful one has to be with their honor and
with their children, and this is somebody who, you know, who abandoned
Torah. למשתבחין בה, L'mishtabchin bah,
those that praise themselves with Torah, those that, you know, sustain the
honor of Torah and stay committed to Torah, על אחת כמה וכמה,
al achat kamah v'khamah, how much more so is the honor that
is due to them? Okay, so again, this interesting ambivalent story that
רבי Rabbi initially felt like, oh, he doesn't deserve, you know, to
have any children alive, and in the end we see, you know,
that look, even the heavens came down to defend his honor. So
again, quite fascinating these, you know, these conflictual attitudes or this ambivalence
towards him. Despite what?
Despite that he left Torah then.
Right, exactly, exactly, exactly. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara switches to the
issue of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר היכי גמר תורה מפומיה
דאחר? Rabbi Meir heichi gmar Torah mipumei d'Acher?
How could רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir learn Torah from אחר? Acher? ואמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah
amar Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbah bar bar Chanah said in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מאי דכתיב, Mai d'khitiv, what's meant by the
verse, כי שפתי כהן ישמרו דעת ותורה יבקשו מפיהו, Ki siftei kohen
yishmeru da'at v'Torah yevakshu mipihu,
because the lips of the כהן Kohen will preserve knowledge and they
will ask instruction, Torah from his mouth, כי מלאך ה' צבאות הוא,
Ki malach Hashem Tzevaot hu, because he's an angel of the Lord
God? So what's the—tell you? It's telling you, אם דומה הרב למלאך
ה' צבאות יבקשו תורה מפיהו. Im domeh harav l'malach Hashem Tzevaot yevakshu
Torah mipihu. If your רבי, Rabbi, your רבי Rabbi is more than
just a teacher. He's supposed to be a model, a religious model.
So if he is similar to an angel of God, then you
can seek Torah from him. An emissary. If—well that, I guess, I
guess that's your פשט. pshat. I don't know if the גמרא Gemara
meant it exactly—I think the גמרא Gemara might have meant it like
simily, like a מלאך. malach. But you're right, that would sort of
bring it a little bit more down to earth. ואם לאו, V'im
lav, but if he's not like a מלאך, malach, אל יבקשו תורה
מפיהו, al yevakshu Torah mipihu, you should not be seeking instruction from
his mouth. It doesn't mean necessarily you have to reject Torah that
you hear from somebody who's not a מלאך, malach, but you shouldn't
be pursuing them. What was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doing pursuing אחר?
Acher?
So אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Resh Lakish, רבי מאיר קרא אשכח ודרש,
Rabbi Meir kra ashkhach v'darash, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir found a פסוק
pasuk and he expounded it to support his approach. הט אזנך ושמע
דברי חכמים ולבך תשית לדעתי. Hatei oznecha u'shema divrei chachamim v'libcha tashit
l'da'ati.
Incline your ear and listen to the words of the sages and
your heart should place your heart to my intent, to
my knowledge. לדעתם לא נאמר *L'da'atam lo ne'emar*, it doesn't say listen
to what their intent, the intent of the sages that teach you,
אלא לדעתי *ela l'da'ati*, my intent. So you can listen to the
sages and still be selective and try to sift out from it
the real sort of divine message, תורה Torah *Torah* message and do
not without having to and be able to be selective and not
necessarily being pulled after all of their attitudes. So it is possible
to listen to sages and to still focus even if even if
their attitudes are not correct. So that's what he says. רב חנינא
מרי הכא *Rav Chanina marei hacha*, רב חנינא *Rav Chanina* said from
the following verse: שמעי בת וראי *Shimi bat u'rei*,
listen my daughter and see, והטי אזנך ושכחי עמך ובית אביך *ve-hati
oznekh ve-shikhchi amekh u-veit avich* and incline your ear and forget your
nation and your father's house. That's a little less clear what it
means forgetting your nation and your father's house, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says it's the same basic point what רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says ומעשיהם
שכחי *ve-ma'aseihem shikhchi*, forget their deeds. So I don't know how their
deeds become your nation and the father's house, but somehow it's the
same idea that you can hone in on the דבר ה׳ *dvar
Hashem* and exclude everything that's extraneous to that from the experience. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קשיא קראי אהדדי *kashya krayei a-hadadi*, now
the verses contradict because these verses indicate that it's acceptable to do
this and the other verse says only if he's similar to an
angel. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא קשיא Lo kashya. הא
בגדול הא בקטן *lo kashya ha b'gadol ha b'katan*, it's the difference
between an adult and a child. A child would be too taken
by and seduced after the רבי Rebbe, *Rebbi* as a whole, whereas
an adult could be able to be more discerning. Now of course
there are different adults, different ways and different stages of adulthood etc.
But it's also about
Yeah so it could mean גדול *gadol* more in terms of stature
than adult, but it seems like it's more about that. I'll mention
in a minute what רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel *Rabbeinu Chananel* says about
all of this. So כי אתא רב דימי אמר amar *ki ata
Rav Dimi amar*, when רב דימי *Rav Dimi* came he said אמרי
במערבא *amri b'ma'arava*, they said in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir אכל תחלא ושדא שיחלא לבר *Rebbi Meir achal tichla ve-shada
shichla l'bar*, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rebbi Meir* ate the date and
he threw out the pits לבר *l'bar*, outside. So דרש רבא *darash
Rava*, so he was able to be selective. דרש רבא מאי דכתיב
mai d'ketiv, *darash Rava mai d'chtiv*, what's meant by the verse אל
גינת אגוז ירדתי לראות באבי הנחל *el ginat egoz yaraditi lirot b'ibei
ha-nachal*, I went down into the garden of the nut garden in
order to see the whatever the plants by the river. למה נמשלו
תלמידי חכמים לאגוז *lama nimshalu talmidei chakhamim l'egoz*, why is a תלמיד
חכם Talmid Chacham *talmid chacham* like a nut? לומר לך מה אגוז
זה אף על פי שמלוכלך בטיט ובצואה אין מה שבתוכו נמאס *loma
lach mah egoz zeh af al pi she-meluchlach b'tit u-v'tzoa ein mah
she-betocho nim'as*, the same even though a nut the husk of the
nut can be disgusting with excrement and dirt but nevertheless the nut
itself is preserved, the meat of the nut is preserved. So אף
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham, אף על פי שסרח אין תורתו נמאסת *af
talmid chacham af al pi she-sarach ein torato nim'eset*, a תלמיד talmid
חכם *talmid chacham* even after he has spoiled and gone off the
דרך derech *derech*, there is his תורה Torah, *Torah* is still preserved.
Now these are potentially very dangerous statements, right? Because you would think
one of the most dangerous people would be somebody who is knowledgeable
in תורה Torah *Torah* and has abandoned that, not just not devoting
their profession to תורה Torah *Torah*, but has really left a life
of observance. This person could be the most pernicious, the most seductive
and pernicious. So and here it's saying no there still is the
תורה Torah. *Torah* in and him might still be preserved and again
this leads to this ambivalence around the story of אחר Acher *Acher*
and the story about רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rebbi Meir* following him.
And רבנו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* is very sort of disturbed by this,
by the implicit message here that an adult can learn תורה Torah
*Torah* from him or and these types of things. So if you
look at the רבנו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* he says I don't know
where to tell you where to start. Line starts with ואף על
גב *ve-af al gav*, it's about three fifths of the way down.
He says ואף על גב דאמרינן רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir קרא אחרינא
אשכח ashkach וסמך עליה דכתיב הט אזנך ושמע דברי חכמים ולבך תשית
לדעתי לדעתם לא נאמר אלא לדעתי מכלל שיש לך לקבל תורתו ולא
דעתו *ve-af al gav d'amrinan Rebbi Meir kra achrina ashkhach v'samach alei
d'chtiv hata oznekha u-shma divrei chakhamim ve-lib'kha tashit l'da'ati l'da'atam lo ne'emar
ela l'da'ati michlal she-yesh l'cha l'kabel torato v'lo da'ato* according to the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ואמרינן קשיא קראי אהדדי *v'amrinan kashya krayei a-hadadi* etc.
בקטן *b'katan* dada dada. So he goes gives the whole גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* and he says even though the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to
say it's okay we're going to see in a גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
later on that אליהו Eliyahu *Eliyahu*'s going to say הא אמר amar
אליהו דאמרי במתיבתא דרקיעא *ha amar Eliyahu d'amri b'mivta d'raki'a*. Well we're
going actually he's going to quote a גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* later on
but I might as well read it to you. He says even
though the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to say it's okay we're going
to see in a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* later on that אליהו *Eliyahu*'s
going to say הא אמר אליהו *ha amar Eliyahu* דאמרי *d'amri* I'm
about ten lines from the bottom in רבנו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel*: במתיבתא
דרקיעא שמעית מכולהו רבנן *b'mivta d'raki'a shema'iti mikulhu rabbanan*, up in the
ישיבה yeshiva *Yeshiva* in heaven they tell over all the teachings of
all the rabbis, ושמעית שמעתא דרבי מאיר משום דגמר מאחר לא אמר
*ve-shema'iti shema'ata d'Rebbi Meir mishum d'gmar me-Acher lo amar*, but they don't
tell over משום דגמר מאחר לא אמר *mishum d'gmar me-Acher lo amar*
but they don't tell over the teachings of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
*Rebbi Meir* because he learned from אחר Acher *Acher*. So you see
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in the end rejects this acceptance of
this approach and אליהו *Eliyahu* tells us in heaven they don't talk
about רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rebbi Meir*'s teachings. ללמדך *L'lamedcha* so it
says הלכתא אפילו גדול ללמוד תורה Torah מחבירו ירא שמים מפי עדיף
ליה *hilchata afilu gadol lilmote torah mi-chavero yerei shamayim mipi adif lei*,
even if an adult to learn תורה Torah, *Torah* from a friend
who is a ירא שמים *yerei shamayim* from his mouth it's better
for him. Now the fascinating thing is it sounds like he was
building it up, right, it seems like he was building it up
to say it's אסור *assur*. Right, I mean, they won't even tell
over רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir teachings in heaven, and he's trying to
reject this, but in the end he winds up with a much
weaker עדיפי adifei is better, I could have figured that out myself.
So anyway, it's quite fascinating, you know, the ambivalence around אחר Acher
and trying to make their peace with how רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
dealt with אחר Acher and so on and that leads to residual
conflictual approaches to somebody who has תורה Torah to teach, but you
know has left the you know has left the path. Now part
of it might be as was said yesterday that אחר Acher was
very specific that he was not
trying specifically proactively trying to prevent people from following him, like that
idea of telling רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir חזור בך chazor becha is
like a brilliant like you know image because it's not just that
he's not trying to seduce people away he's actually trying to you
know push people back, don't follow me into the wrong דרך derech?
you know, so that wasn't being misled to like abandon a life
of תורה, Torah but it would even accidentally doing the sin, he
says don't follow me you know, and because of that it might
have been more acceptable. Look you know there are people nowadays, there
are scholars in תלמוד Talmud that are not observant and that have
a lot of interesting תורה Torah to teach you know, we're not
supposed to learn from them, so there might really be a difference
between whether it's a context of the person and their teachings and
who they are and whatever, trying to seduce people away or just
presenting תורה Torah and not interested in you know in bringing people
away from a life of תורה. Torah Yes.
I was thinking of the apostates in the Middle Ages who converted
to Christianity and actively did danger to us on the outside.
Right, so sometimes right, so people that are invested in actually taking
people away from תורה Torah are the most dangerous if they're תורה
Torah, scholars and they're knowledgeable and so on. But you know I
think that's an important qualification that אחר Acher. was דווקא davka trying
to prevent people from following him. Yes Micah.
Well I mean the parallel to אחר Acher saying don't follow me
is רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir trying to bring him into גן עדן
Gan Eden in some sense.
Right, that's a nice point too.
What I understand though is like, and I don't know if it's
something that you can, I'm not sure how that's possible, like is
that a disincentive for me to do מצוות mitzvos and תורה, Torah,
like okay well someone can bring me into גן עדן, Gan Eden,
how does that work?
Yeah I mean again I mean after all this whole period of
and how I don't know I mean look you know and how
much גן עדן Gan Eden does he get and after this whole
period and I'm you know anyway I don't think the גמרא Gemara
at that in that stage, it's always interesting to think how much
is the גמרא Gemara sort of thinking about the the you know
the impact of its teaching or how much is it just sort
of you know really unpacking its own sort of theological and religious
reflections on the issue, and I think that they were very conflicted
about אחר. Acher Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this
back to the
גמרא. Gemara Okay, I jump back to רבנו חננאל because now we're
going to have the story he referred to. אשכח רבה בר שילא
Rabba bar Shila לאליהו l'Eliyahu so רבה בר שילא Rabba bar Shila
found אליהו אמר ליה amar lei מאי קא עביד הקדוש ברוך הוא
mai ka-avid Hakadosh Baruch Hu what's God doing אמר ליה amar lei
קאמר שמעתתא מפומייהו דכולהו רבנן ka'amar shmaattah mipumaihu de'chul-hu rabbanan he's telling
over the the teachings of all the rabbis, you gotta love the
image right that God is teaching over the teachings of the rabbis
that's a real like לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim hi type of
a story ומפומיה דרבי מאיר לא קאמר u'mipumei de'Rebbi Meir lo ka'amar
and he's not telling over stories from the from the mouth of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, אמר ליה amar lei אמאי amai why so
he said משום דקא גמר שמעתתא מפומיה דאחר mishum de'ka'gamar shmaattah mipumei
de'Acher because he learned teachings from the mouth of אחר Acher and
by the way the the implication seems to be that he's not
just not telling over אחר's Acher תורה Torah that came via רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir he's not telling over any of רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir תורה Torah because it's the whole thing you know it invalidated
everything of רבי מאיר at least it didn't bring it was enough
to keep it out of the ישיבה yeshiva in heaven, it didn't
invalidate it but it kept it out of the ישיבה of heaven.
So doesn't that make the entire anonymous statements of the משנה Mishnah
are from רבי מאיר and doesn't quote his name?
Well that's also true but that's a different story that's not the
אחר Acher?
story the reason no I understand but it's ironic right?
Right רבי מאיר right that is the סתם משנה stam Mishnah story
right right exactly exactly. So I think that that might also be
you know I but I think that that might be also dealing
with like this issue like you know so right there's one thing
about how we deal with it down here and there's another thing
with how they deal with it up in heaven and you know
it's again trying to work through that ambivalence, but yes that's a
very legitimate point that it pushes off the problem to heaven not
to down here.
What though the argument here might be about what's the nature of
תורה Torah and מסורה. Mesorah. Are you just you know teaching what
you heard from your teacher in which case we have to preserve
that because
you're just a vehicle there's none of you in it so
in that case you know then קאמר שמעתתא ka'amar shmaattah whatever רבי
מאיר learned he learned from אחר Acher, and that's why רבונו של
עולם Ribono Shel Olam wouldn't repeat it. But if it's more you
know if there's more creative aspects and so on then that's more
dangerous and you know that doesn't fit into this story.
Right right right. But I think that's a good point like when
it says the תורה Torah, isn't sort of made you know isn't
ruined it's inside the shell like the nut is in the shell
is that because you know he's got a מסורה Mesorah and the
actual you know he's just a vehicle for transmitting it but if
you see תורה Torah as more of a creative act then you
know you are more worried about the personality of the one that
is you know working it through so I think that's also an
excellent point. Okay so let's move on so the גמרא Gemara says
like this okay
אמר ליה amar lei אמאי. amai. So who was it said to?
רבה בר שילא *Rabba bar Shila* said to אליהו *Eliyahu*, why is
that a problem? רבי מאיר רימון מצא *Rabbi Meir rimon matza*. He
found a pomegranate, right, this is better than the date, because the
pomegranate also symbolizes often like filled with מצוות *mitzvot*. So it’s also
like ironic or, you know, certainly an interesting choice. רימון מצא *Rimon
matza*, תוכו אכל *tocho achal*, he ate the he ate the seeds,
קליפתו זרק *klipato zarak*, and he threw out the rind. אמר ליה
amalei *Amar leh*, so אליהו *Eliyahu* said back to him, השתא קאמר
*hasha kamar*, so you know what, that was a good point, and
now up in heaven God is saying, מאיר בני אומר *Meir bni
omer*, here’s what מאיר *Meir* says, and they’re quoting רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*. So it’s so funny, right, again, like, you know, this little
point that that he made. Oh, yeah, טאקע *tacka*, I didn't realize
that. So now they're going to change what they do up in
heaven. But it also shows how רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel *Rabbeinu Chananel*,
even though trying to come out like לחומרא *l'chumra*, you know, in
the end the story here ends that רב מאיר *Rav Meir* is
quoted. And let's see what they say. What?
It's not so easy to take the seeds out of a pomegranate.
Right. It's easier to throw it away and buy...
That's a good point. It's a good point. Only רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* could take the seeds out of the pomegranate. That's a good
point. And what is God saying now up in heaven, the teaching
that he's teaching in the name of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*? Here's
what he's saying. He’s saying, מאיר בני אומר *Meir bni omer*, בזמן
שאדם מצטער *bizman she'adam mitzta'er*, when a person is in is in
pain, שכינה מה לשון אומרת *Shchina mah lashon omeret*? קלני מראשי קלני
מזרועי *Kalani me-roshi kalani me-zero-i*. I have been made light from my
head, light from my arm, which means it’s like a euphemism, means
heavy. Like God is saying, "אוי *oy*, my head hurts, my arm
hurts." God is there suffering with us. אם כך kach הקדוש ברוך
הוא מצטער על דמם של רשעים reshaim, *Im kacha Hakadosh Baruch Hu
mitzta'er al damam shel resha'im*, and if that’s how God’s pained even
when wicked—now we didn't say wicked, but now we're throwing it in,
there seems an obvious point of specifically this teaching—קל וחומר על דמם
של צדיקים שנשפך *kal vachomer al damam shel tzaddikim shenispach*. How much
more so is does God suffer when it is the צדיקים *tzaddikim*
who have been murdered? So also we switched from being in pain
to being to their blood and being murdered. So it’s a very
strange like little teaching, but it does also seem to be the
point, you know, that there it is, that even people that are
not צדיקים *tzaddikim*, God feels their pain and their suffering. And again,
you know, about אחר Acher? *Acher*, you know, this sort of, you
know, we can't just be completely dismissive. Like even God feels the
pain of wicked, and, you know, so again it seems to be
an allusion to אחר Acher, *Acher* and to having to be have
a sense of, you know, still still valuing and still and having
some some sympathy for him. So when they chose to teach a
teaching of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* in up in heaven, this was
the teaching that they taught, the one that relates to this type
of empathy. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
אשכחיה שמואל לרב יהודה *Asha'ei Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda*, שמואל *Shmuel* found רב
יהודה *Rav Yehuda* דתלי בעיברא דדשא *d'tali b'eivra d'dasha*, he was like
leaning on the like a bolt of a of a gate, of
the door, וקא בכי *v'kabachi*, and he was crying. אמר ליה Amar
lei, *Amar leh*, he said to him, שינינא Shinina, *shinina*, like smart
one, מאי קא בכית *mai kabachis*? why are you crying? אמר ליה
*Amar leh*, מי זוטרא מאי דכתיב ורבנן *mi zutra mai d'chtiv u'rabbanan*?
Is it trivial what’s written by the Rabbis? איה סופר איה שוקל
איה סופר את המגדלים *Ayei sofer ayei shokel ayei sofer tamigdalim*? Where
is the scribe, where is the weigher, where is the one who
counts the castles? What does this mean? איה סופר *Ayei sofer*, שהיו
סופרים כל אותיות שבתורה *she'hayu sofrim kol otiyot she'ba'Torah*, that it used
to be like, you know, that the, you know, before the destruction
of the Temple, that they were such of a great level that
they, you know, counted they all the letters all the letters of
the תורה Torah? *Torah*. Of course, that was the whole enterprise of
the Masoretes, you know, which reactionally that actually have was done. איה
שוקל *Ayei shokel*, שהיו שוקלים קלים וחמורים שבתורה *she'hayu shoklim kalim va'chamurim
she'ba'Torah*. They would sort of weigh, you know, the קל וחומר *kal
va'chomer*. You have to know what's light and what's heavy to make
a קל וחומר *kal va'chomer*. איה סופר את המגדלים *Ayei sofer tamigdalim*,
where are the ones that count the castles? שהיו שונים גמל מאות
הלכות במגדל הפורח באויר *She'hayu shonim gimel me'ot halachot b'migdal haporeiach ba'avir*.
They would even study 300 laws—300 is always an exaggeration—about the castle
floating in the air. So talk about making castles in the in
the clouds, castle in the air. Now some say that actually רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says it shouldn't be that floats in the air, it
should say that opens up into the air, and it refers to
a משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* in אהלות *Ohalot* that deals with like a
chest, which is called a מגדל *migdal*, that is half inside the
house and half outside the house and does the טומאה *tumah* transfer
from inside the house to outside the house.
Okay. I saw that before, that he says היתר דריזין פורחים
באויר *hater d'rizin porchim ba'avir*. Ah, that’s true. That's a good point.
פורחים באויר *Porchim ba'avir*, evoking the פורחים באויר *porchim ba'avir*. Very good
point. Okay. ואמר Ve'amar רבי אמי *V'amar Rabbi Ami*, תלת מאה בעיי
בעו דואג ואחיתופל במגדל הפורח באויר *tlata me'a bayei badug v'achitofel b'migdal
haporeiach ba'avir*. They had 300 דואג ואחיתופל *Doeg and Achitofel*, who were
like the תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* but but רשעים *resha'im*,
they asked, you know, 300 questions about this castle floating in the
air. ותנן *V'tnan*, and even so we teach, גמל מלכים וארבעה הדיוטות
אין להם חלק לעולם הבא *gimel melachim v'arba hedyotot ein lahem chelek
l'olam haba*, three kings and four commoners don't have a portion to
the world to come, of which דואג ואחיתופל *Doeg and Achitofel* are
two of them. So if that’s true, if they were, you know,
of such great תורה Torah *Torah* and nevertheless, you know, they were
able to like go off the דרך derech? *derech*, so it says,
אנן מה תהא עלן *anan ma te'hei alan*? We, what will be,
what will be, you know, what will be with us? I mean,
if somebody like an אחר Acher, *Acher* and somebody like these people,
these enormous תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* could go off the דרך derech.
*derech*, what hope do we have? Okay, to stay on the דרך
*derech* even with all of our
תורה Torah *Torah*.
Right,
so basically, yeah, I mean I think it's just because it was
a way to get into the דואג ואחיתופל part and that they
were רשעים, okay? I don't think it's to get into like the
what we've lost in the חורבן הבית Churban Habayis part. It's about
more like, you know, how could people be so great and have
gone off the דרך? So, you know, unless ישעיה Yeshaya himself can
be seen as mourning that it's not a result of the
חורבן, Churban, but it's a result of the רשעות, rishus, you know,
that people were—the perversion of the time, right? So anyway, so it
says, okay, so אמר ליה so he said to him, שינינא, sharp
one, טינא הייתה בליבם. tina hayisa belibam. It wasn't that, you know,
the problem was was that they had some corruption in their heart
to begin with. Like, you know, there
was—that they were born that way, but
it's like—if like—it wasn't that, you know, they were totally pure and
learned תורה Torah and then they were, you know, some—and something external
to them pulled them away, you know. They always—these people had, you
know, had their own lusts and desires and types of things that
were from the very beginning. And that was what—what? Yeah, whatever, something
like that, right. So, הייתה בליבם. hayisa belibam. אחר מאי? Acher mai?
So what was the story by אחר? Acher זמר יווני לא פסק
מפומיה. zemer yavani lo fasak mipumei. The Greek song never stopped from
his mouth, which is really, you know, think about the phrase before
about תרבות רעה, tarbus ra'ah, which nowadays תרבות tarbus means culture, right?
So he was just—he was very attracted to the Greek Hellenistic culture.
So, you know, if you keep yourself really on the narrow, you
know, path, you'll stay pure, you'll stay protected. It's that they had
other things that they were interested in that eventually worked their way,
you know, and ultimately pulled them off the path. So אמרו עליו
על אחר, amru aleiv al Acher, they said by אחר, Acher בשעה
שהיה עומד מבית המדרש, besha'ah shehayah omeid mibeis hamedrash, when he would
stand up from the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, הרבה ספרי מינים נושרים
מחיקו. harbei sifrei minim noshrim micheiko. So a lot of like—they would
stand up and out of his lap, one wonders like if he
was hiding it under the גמרא, Gemara you know. So a lot
of—a lot of, you know, right, Greek philosophy books or maybe מינים,
minim, you know, who knows what it is, you know, whether it's
Christian—you know, Jewish-Christian literature etc. But anyway, but presumably more it's Greek,
you know, Greek philosophy books would fall—would fall out from an—and a
scene that I remember from As Driven Leaf that was illustrated well
over there. So it's actually quite fascinating, right? Because how do you—again,
how do you deal with this phenomenon of אחר? Acher How do
you deal with such a תלמיד חכם going off the דרך? And
before we had it like it was a result of
a—of like—of a mystical experience which he wasn't able to properly understand
and led to heresy. And here, it's a very different explanation, attracted
by this culture, and part of being attracted by the culture, it
doesn't start necessarily by an intellectual attraction, right? If you talk about
nowadays what leads kids to, you know, they go to college to
leave—you know, to leave a life of observance and so whatever, sometimes
it's because I don't know they're introduced to challenging philosophies or biblical
criticism, and very often it's because of the seductions of the outside
culture. And sometimes it's because the two of them work together, you
know, because you're attracted to everything the other world has to offer,
these types of problems eat away at you more and ultimately they
pull you away. You know, there's a—there's a story about one of
the—that some משכילים maskilim came to—I forget who it was, I think
it was about the וילנא גאון, Vilna Gaon, they came to him
and they, you know, and they say like—I have, you know—I have
so many questions, so many questions. Like if somebody would just answer
my questions, you know, I'd be—I'd be פרום. frum. So it goes
to—you know, goes to the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon and he asks
him like all of his questions and the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon
refuses to—to answer. So he—he walks away. So a תלמיד said, רבי,
you—you know everything, why didn't you answer his questions? He said, those
weren't questions, they were answers. Ta-da!
So
there you go.
Okay, but which doesn't mean—which doesn't mean that people don't often have
very legitimate questions, but you know, the point is that some—you know,
the relationship between what's bothering us religiously and philosophically and what sort
of is, you know, attracting us to the attract—you know, to the
range of attractions, not necessarily hedonistic, but to the range of, you
know, attractions of the outside world, I think that this is a
very fascinating, you know, sort of insight or approach into what's going
on with אחר, Acher yes.
Wasn't the מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevukhim written precisely for intelligent people wrestling
with these questions?
Yes, yes, but no, the point of that story was was that
the questions came as a—as an—as a basis for—it starts with I
don't want to be פרום frum and then questions, right? מעשר? Ma'aser?
Right, exactly. Right, there are very legitimate philosophical questions, whatever they have
to be engaged, but again, this here, and you know, and it
sort of started essentially with that, although in a mystical context, but
it started to all be purely intellectual, and here you have the
juxtaposition of Greek song with books of מינים minim fell out of
his lap. But the first problem, says the גמרא, Gemara was the
Greek song, right? It doesn't say טינא הייתה בליבו tina hayisa belibo
because he was reading ספרי מינים, sifrei minim, right? The טינא הייתה
בליבו—so tina hayisa belibo I think again, it's like a really fascinating
perspective. What?
Then he was drawn after the philosophy.
Exactly. It's exactly what I'm saying.
So no pun intended, but isn't the term שיננא Shinnena have sort
of a bite to it?
Yeah, there's a question about whether that's meant as a compliment or
as a little bit of a critique.
Okay. Alright. So, now, I've got to just tell you though, רש"י
Rashi is I find it like, like quite humorous the way רש"י,
Rashi the approach that רש"י Rashi takes on this. רש"י Rashi says:
זמר יווני לא פסק מביתו, Zemer Yavani lo pasak mibeito, והיה לו
להניח בשביל חורבן הבית, vehaya lo lehaniach bishvil churban habayit, דכתיב בשיר
לא ישתו יין. dichtiv bashir lo yishtu yayin. The problem was that
he wasn't properly mourning over חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayit. Somehow, I think
that it's a little bit more than that. I think it's not
just שיר shir but it's שיר יווני. Shir Yavani. זמר יווני לא
פסק, Zemer Yavani lo pasak, זמר יווני לא פסק מביתו. Zemer Yavani
lo pasak mibeito. Okay. So anyway, I think רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel?
says something on this. He says, what does he say?
No, where was
רבינו חננאל?
Rabbeinu Chananel, So רש"י Rashi emphasizes לא פסק. lo pasak. That's רש"י's
Rashi emphasis is לא פסק lo pasak is the important phrase.
Yeah, but still, he doesn't emphasize the problem of יווני.
Yavani. Right, so by emphasizing לא פסק, lo pasak, the זמר יווני
Zemer Yavani becomes less of a problem?
Well, I don't, right, but I just don't think that's פשט. pshat.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמרו עליו על אחר, Amru
alav al Acher, they said about אחר, Acher, בשעה שהיה עומד מבית
המ, besha'ah shehaya omed mibeit ham, oh
we just did that. Okay. שאלו נימוס הגרדי את רבי מאיר. Sha'alu
Nimus HaGardi et Rabbi Meir. So נימוס Nimus the weaver asked רבי
מאיר, כל עמר דנחית ליורה סליק, kol amar denachis leyoreh salik, is
it true that every wool that goes into the dyeing pot comes
out well-dyed? אמר ליה, he said to him, כל מה דהוה נקי
אגב אמיה, kol ma dahavei naki agav imei, anything that was clean
when it was sort of sheared from its mother, from the lamb,
so if it's good quality wool, סליק, salik, then it'll come out
and the dye will hold fast when it comes out of the
dyeing pot. כל דלא הוה נקי אגב אמיה, kol delo havei naki
agav imei, anything that was not clean, you know, when the actual
original raw ingredients, you can't make a good recipe if you don't
start with good raw ingredients, if the wool itself was not clean,
לא סליק, lo salik, it won't come out with the dye holding
fast to the wool, presumably an issue about if somebody who is
immersing themselves in a life of תורה, Torah how is it that
the תורה, Torah shouldn't the תורה Torah. stick to that person and
change the person? And the answer is, it depends what ingredients you're
putting in to begin with, right? And that's the issue about the
טינא הייתה בלבו. tina haisa belibo. So if there was something wrong
with the character to begin with, תורה Torah will not necessarily transform,
which is by the way an interesting admission. You know, I mean
תורה Torah can be transformative, but like not always, you know, in
terms of religions in general. You know, some people, you know, religion
can help a certain segment of people and תורה, Torah whatever, but
there, but you know, it won't always be transformative and if you
come in in a certain way you might not leave changed, you
know, it might, you know, maybe you'll be changed somewhat but not
totally and so on. So it's quite a, I think a powerful
image, yes.
תוספות Tosafot says that נימוס הגרדי Nimus HaGardi was a Greek philosopher
who was an opponent of paganism.
Interesting. So how does he understand, what does, but does he read
the discussion in the same way about תורה and immersing oneself in
תורה?
Yeah, it's about the nature versus nurture sort of a factor.
Oh, yeah, yeah, it is. That's what I'm saying. Right. I mean,
you're right, right, I mean that's exactly what I'm saying, except I'm
framing it not just in terms of general nurture but in terms
of the power of religion and תורה to transform somebody. Right, you
know, it's like somebody says, well, how do you expect me to
care about, like, you know, to want to be a פרום frum
Jew if you see all of these rabbis that, you know, do
these terrible things and so on. The point is, like, can you,
can you rely on religion to totally transform, you know, human nature?
You know, so it's, you know, hopefully it makes, you know, it
does make incremental changes in people and hopefully people that are, you
know, good people to begin with get enriched, you know, and nurtured
by it, but it's unrealistic to expect that, you know, that it
will be totally transformative. People are still people. Yes, Michael. It's in
the future, right? God says והסירותי את לב האבן, vahasiroti es lev
ha'even, you know, ומל השם אלוקיך את לבבך. umal Hashem Elokecha es
levavecha. You know, in this world that doesn't happen, you know, it
maybe happens in small measures and that's where we have to do
תשובה teshuva and work on it if we want it to happen.
Yes.
It even means to some extent to what, but you know, what
he, what רבי מאיר is saying is that you have to forget,
it's almost when you're born, it's how you were born. Yeah, but
I don't see them saying, I don't see it saying totally like,
oh it, you know, from the time he was an infant. You
know, I mean, that was, you know, whatever.
Think about the ירושלמי Yerushalmi story, right? That his father...
Yeah, so that's the ירושלמי Yerushalmi story, but I don't see that
here in the בבלי.
Bavli. And it was one thing, but this is the same רבי
מאיר who kept on trying to bring אחר Acher later, you know,
אחר Acher to the, right? Right, later, like, oh you too חזור
חזור, chazor chazor, but he didn't give up on him. So here
too it's like he's saying, "Alright, well, you know..."
No, no, no, no, because there's a different thing. Meaning there's one
question which is: how do you deal with the religious challenge that
תורה did not, that this enormity of somebody, you know, being such
a huge תלמיד חכם, he didn't, it didn't keep him on the
right דרך. And that's a question about the power of תורה and
you have to address that. You have to address how is it
that תורה does not preserve somebody, somebody's being a פרום frum person?
Okay, but that does not mean that even if now we come
up with an explanation... Well you know I mean אחר Acher had
his own lusts and desires and intellectual and other types of
attractions and תורה cannot always be totally transformative. So now we've preserved,
we've answered the theological question about תורה. It doesn't mean that we're
saying that אחר acher was a רשע, rasha, okay? So I mean
there are different issues that are being addressed. Yes.
This seems to be a problem with the idea if you learn
תורה for the wrong reasons, eventually you'll learn it for the right
reasons.
Right, so you know again, there I mean there's all this thing
like דווקא davka Judaism is so much in תורה ומצוות Torah and
mitzvos is about as you said, that's excellently put, מתוך שלא לשמה
בא לשמה mitoch shelo lishmah ba lishmah and wherever your sort of
emotions and motivations are, hopefully your actions shape them, but it's not
magic, you know, so, right, okay, so, okay. בעצם, Be-etzem, moving on,
okay, I think that was a very good unpacking of that story.
Let's now get, now we did בן זומא ואחר Ben Zoma and
Acher and now we move to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so
we have 22 minutes to do the דף. Daf. Okay, so רבי
עקיבא עלה בשלום וירד בשלום. Rabbi Akiva ala beshalom veyarad beshalom. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva went up in peace and came down in peace.
This just even starting with this part of it, it added the
words of עלה בשלום, ala beshalom, right, which we didn't have that
before, because he came in in a complete state, he was able
to come out unscathed. Okay, also especially what we just said about
אחר, acher about אחר acher having been conflicted or אחר having been,
you know, having something not complete within him, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
was complete and therefore came out complete.
ועליו הכתוב אומר, Ve'alav hakatuv omer, regarding him the verse says, משכני
אחריך נרוצה, moshcheini acharecha narutza, draw me after you and after you
I will run. So again, very interesting because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
was very big into שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim, כל השירים קודש ושיר
השירים קודש קודשים, kol hashirim kodesh veShir HaShirim kodesh kodashim, understanding שיר
השירים Shir HaShirim to be a משל mashal of God and בני
ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, particularly probably of mystical significance, you know, you know
meaning. And here saying that, you know, that the idea for some
people, for some people, you know, you're supposed to be guarded and
pull yourself back with that encounter from God. You're not ready for
it. רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, all he needed was that little like
little pull and then he's should be running, you know, because he's
in the stage where God just has to draw him near and
then and then he's allowed to run to pursue. ואף רבי עקיבא,
Ve-af Rabbi Akiva, ביקשו מלאכי השרת לדוחפו, bikshu malachei hasharei lidoffo, but
even רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even though God was like beckoning him
on and he was like running to for this encounter, the angels
were trying to push him away. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar
lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu, God said to them, הניחו לזקן זה, hanichu
lazaken zeh, let go, you know, don't stand in the way of
this of this sage, שראוי להשתמש בכבודי, sheraui lehishtamesh bichvodi,
he is fit to use my honor. Now that is a very
strange phrase, to use my honor, להשתמש, lehishtamesh, you know, again like
it might mean, you know, just the sense of being having that
intimacy with God means that somehow you are basking in it and
there's a sense there of being משתמש, mishtamesh, but the
רבינו חננאל גירסא Rabbeinu Chananel's girsa is ראוי הוא, raui hu, you
see the last three words on this page of רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu
Chananel ראוי הוא להסתכל בכבודי, raui hu lehistakel bichvodi, he is fit
to gaze on my כבוד, kavod, right? כבוד, Kavod, the כבוד kavod
of God is understood to be actually some physical thing like וכבוד
ה' נראה בענן. vechvod Hashem ne'era be'anan. So for him it was
more about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva can have this vision, right, which
is the vision the problem with בן זומא Ben Zoma was הציץ
ונפגע, hetzitz venifga, peered and he wasn't ready to peer. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is fit to have this, to have this perception.
And then the angel says, what about the other one?
Oh, because they didn't push the others away enough, maybe.
Or maybe that the angels that God
didn't
prevent the angels from letting the others through, right, right, or unless
the angels were peaking through even as they were being pushed away.
Okay. מאי דרש, Mai darash, so, so what you know, so, so
how what did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva understand based on the verse
that that what? So the, we'll see the verses, but the simple
understanding is that allowed him, the way רש"י Rashi says, not to
fall into the same type of error that אחר fell, that he
thought he saw מטטרון Metatron and he thought that מטטרון Metatron was
some other type of a deity. So how did he know better
to see the right thing? אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, because the verse
says, ואתה מרבבות קודש. ve-ata meirevivot kodesh. So what does it mean
ואתה? ve-ata? אות הוא, Ot hu, the word אתה, ata, אות הוא,
ot hu, it is a sign ברבבה שלו, berivavo shelo, in God's,
you know, myriads. What does that mean? That means that God is,
you know, you can sort of discern God from amongst the other
angels and there's a way to discern and he obviously saw that
this מטטרון Metatron guy was very was similar to the other angels,
so clearly was not another deity because God will always be very
distinct from the angels. I got to tell you, I'm going to
find the next lines of גמרא Gemara deeply disturbing because just the
very sense that you need to see a to see a to
see oh well you can check you can know who God is,
He's the one wearing the red carnation, you know, it's like, you
know, you'd think that but maybe the גמרא Gemara is trying to
say more than that, like God is so you know completely the
vision of God is so qualitatively completely different than the encounter with
angels that he knew this is why רש"י says that מטטרון Metatron
could not have been a divinity.
For רבי אבהו אמר Rabbi Abahu amar what? He's easy
to, you know...
Right, right. No I understand, I understand, but I'm just saying here
it's discerning God from it seems from the heavenly retinue. Like how
do you know which is an angel and which is God? That
seems to be the way רש"י is reading it because of the
whole מטטרון Metatron problem that מטטרון Metatron אחר confused as a deity.
So right okay fine anyway let's read the גמרא Gemara let's read
this a little bit more. ורבי אבהו VeRabbi Abbahu אמר דגומר מרבבה.
dagumir me-revava. Again שיר השירים Shir Hashirim so דוגמא הוא ברבבה שלו.
dugma hu be-revava shelo. God is a דוגמא dugma so which is
an interesting word because דוגמא's dugma usually a model after which you
pattern other things, but here it's being used as a way of
distinguish, you know, something in even amongst God's myriad. ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish אמר ה' צבאות שמו Hashem Tzeva'ot Shemo אדון הוא בצבא שלו.
adon hu betzeva shelo.
God is clearly the master amongst his hosts and you can identify
God. So, ורבי חייא בר אבא VeRabbi Chiya bar Abba אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan לא ברוח ה' lo beruach Hashem ואחר הרוח
רעש ve-achar haruach ra'ash לא ברעש ה' lo beruash Hashem ואחר הרעש
אש ve-achar hara'ash esh לא באש ה' lo ba'esh Hashem ואחר האש
קול דממה דקה ve-achar ha'esh kol demama daka והנה ה' עובר vehine
Hashem over or לא והנה ה' עובר lo vehine Hashem over from
an earlier verse
which means that all of these types of things the and the
מהרש"א Maharsha says
the the angels of wind the angels of fire all these things
are not God, God has to be seeked out in a very
different type of an encounter. So רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva knew that
all these angels and all this sort of you know you know
right all of this type
of revelation that he was having and you
know mystical experience he knew that it was not God that God
was something other than all of that and therefore he was not
led astray.
Okay so
God what?
You can't quote this פסוק pasuk here and not see the word
אחר in it.
Oh that's interesting and אחר that's fascinating. Okay I want to read
you very quickly because actually this is from האזינו Ha'azinu which is
what we're coming up to this quote
of
like אסאמיר ואבדיש קודש asamer ve'avdesh kodesh and I don't know if
I had remembered or I guessed that this was developed in the
ספרי Sifrei and it was because what bothers me I gotta tell
you about this is words like דוגמא dugma or words like אסא
asah which is spelled as the same as אתה atah to me
sound very like you know anthropomorphic like you know human beings בצלם
אלוקים betzelem Elokim and God you know and דוגמא dugma I mean
what's God a דוגמא dugma of maybe of the human form? Anyway
but the so I wonder if that's the subtext going on here.
The ספרי Sifrei though is you know is very much along the
lines of רש"י's explanation. Here's what it says אסאמיר ואבדיש קודש asamer
ve'avdesh kodesh although let's be for signs if you want to see
more of it it has a you know I have some copies.
מלך בשר ודם melech basar vadam יושב בתוך פלטין שלו. yoshev betoch
platin shelo. A human king is in the middle of
his like פלטין platiyo which is like whatever like a courtyard. יש
בו בני אדם נאים ממנו yesh bo bnei adam na'im mimenu there'll
be people that look more handsome than the king, בני אדם משובחים
ממנו bnei adam shebachim mimenu people even maybe more praiseworthy than the
king, בני אדם גבורים ממנו bnei adam gibborim mimenu אבל מי שאמר
והיה העולם aval mi she'amar vehayah ha'olam אינו כן eino kein אלא
ואסאמיר ואבדיש קודש ella ve'asamer ve'avdesh kodesh אות הוא ot hu the
אות הוא בתוך רבבות קודש. ot hu betoch rivevot kodesh.
He is God is distinguished even amongst the you know you have
all the angels you'll know who God is. וכשנגלה על הים מיד
הכירו uchshe-niglah al hayam miyad hikkiru and that's why they could see
identify God as it says זה אלי ואנוהו אלוקי אבי וארוממנהו. ze
Eli ve'anveihu Elokei avi va'aromemenhu. כך okay and then it goes on
and on. So again it's a fascinating issue like if you are
having this mystical experience and seeing the divine retinue you know you're
very likely to confuse these angels with God and are you of
a level that you will be able to know even though I'm
seeing all of these angelic beings this isn't God. God is something
completely different than all of this.
Right he used the term דוגמא dugma for for he's have
forgeries how most people can't tell them from the original.
Oh that's interesting.
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
could tell between the original and the forgery.
And the אות ot being very small. Sometimes there's what you think
to be true and what's not.
Right I think that's what איוב Job is saying that what makes
for ever right so if you talk about it more intellectually like
like just intellectual error and the difference between truth and falsehood right.
But I guess what I'm bothered with more is not translating this
as intellectual and theological error but as the sense of actually this
much more I'm trying I'm treating it a little more literal in
terms of this you know anthropomorphizing this whole experience and an actual
vision of God and then seeing God there surrounded by God's angels
and having a hard time figuring out which one is God and
which one is the angel. But you're right I mean translated theologically
and intellectually it's making a very powerful point about how much how
hard it is to you know that those tiny errors can you
know lead right can can be enormous.
Yes I think that's appropriate for ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana.
Identifying God?
Yeah okay because of מלכות? Malchut? All right תנו רבנן Tnu Rabbanan
ששה דברים נאמרו בשדים. shishah devarim neemru bashedim. Now this is nothing
to do with anything that preceded. You might remember that all of
this was a digression of the fact that we are not supposed
to talk about about מעשה מרכבה. Ma'aseh Merkavah. So we have a
story of פרדס. Pardes. The story of פרדס Pardes is over. Now
we are going back to one final ברייתא Braita about מעשה מרכבה
Ma'aseh Merkavah which deals with also angels and now we're going to
talk about angels and שדים shedim for a brief moment, okay? Don't
try to connect this to the previous discussion. If you can, you
want a prize. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. שישה דברים נאמרו בשדים. Shisha
Devarim Neemru Bashedim. Six things were said about the שדים.
shedim. How is this connected to what we...?
שלושה כמלאכי השרת ושלושה כבני אדם. Shlosha Kemaleihei Hashares Ushlosha Kivnei Adam.
Three like the heavenly angels and three like humans. שלושה כמלאכי השרת,
Shlosha Kemaleihei Hashares, three like the heavenly angels: יש להם כנפיים כמלאכי
השרת, Yesh Lahem Knafayim Kemaleihei Hashares, they have wings, וטסין מסוף העולם
ועד סופו כמלאכי השרת, Vetasin Misof Haolam Vead Sofo Kemaleihei Hashares, they
can fly from one end of the world to the next, ויודעין
מה שעתיד להיות כמלאכי השרת, Veyodin Mah Sheasid Lihyos Kemaleihei Hashares, and
they know the future like angels. So someone says, יודעין סלקא דעתך?
Yodin Salka Deitach? They know? Like they have the intrinsic ability to
see the future? אלא שומעין מאחורי הפרגוד כמלאכי השרת. Ela Shomin Meachorei
Hapargod Kemaleihei Hashares. No, no, no, they don't know and neither do
the heavenly angels. They just hear from behind the divine, from behind
the curtain. So they're informed about the future, not that they themselves
are able to see the future. Okay. ושלושה כבני אדם, Ushlosha Kivnei
Adam, three like humans: אוכלין ושותין כבני אדם, Ochlin Veshotin Kivnei Adam,
they eat and drink like humans, פרין ורבין כבני אדם, Parin Veravin
Kivnei Adam,
they procreate like humans, humans and I mean also presumably have sex
and that they procreate, ומתים כבני אדם, Umesim Kivnei Adam, and actually
שדים shedim actually die. Angels don't die, שדים shedim die. שישה דברים
נאמרו בבני אדם. Shisha Devarim Neemru Bevnei Adam. Now six things were
said about humans: שלושה כמלאכי השרת ושלושה כבהמה, Shlosha Kemaleihei Hashares Ushlosha
Keveheimah, three like angels and three like animals, right? And this is
the whole fascinating aspect, right, of נברא בצלם אלוהים Nivra Betzelem Elokim
but we also have a body. You know, there's a beautiful, by
the way,
פשט, pshat, I don't know if it's פשט pshat at all, that
says, I forgot who says it, I think it's רב יוסף בכור
שור Rav Yosef Bechor Shor on the פסוק pasuk נעשה אדם בצלמנו
Na'aseh Adam Betzalmeinu that God, what's the נעשה na'aseh in the plural?
That God is talking to the land, to the earth, and he's
saying, hey, let's be partners in this. You provide the body and
I'll provide the soul. Okay, so this whole idea of being partly
animalistic and partly divine, you know, and part spirit. Okay, so six
things are said by humans, three they're like the angels and
three they're like the animals. So what is it? שלושה כמלאכי השרת:
Shlosha Kemaleihei Hashares: יש להם דעת כמלאכי השרת, Yesh Lahem Da'as Kemaleihei
Hashares, they have intellect, ומהלכין בקומה זקופה כמלאכי השרת, Umehalchin Bekomah Zkufah
Kemaleihei Hashares, they walk upright like angels, okay, which also speaks about
I think human dignity, ומספרים בלשון הקודש כמלאכי השרת, Umesaprim Belashon Hakodesh
Kemaleihei Hashares, and they speak in Hebrew. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says
not all humans speak in Hebrew but okay, but the angels speak
in Hebrew, but it means that they have a spoken language. So
again, this is really, you know, very signs of what it means
to be human.
ושלושה כבהמה, Ushlosha Keveheimah, and three like animals: אוכלין ושותין כבהמה, Ochlin
Veshotin Keveheimah, פרין ורבין כבהמה, Parin Veravin Keveheimah, they eat and drink,
they have sex and they procreate, ומוציאין רעי כבהמה, Umotzi'in Re'i Keveheimah,
and they actually, you know, defecate. So there's something that is very,
you know, physical about them and animalistic and there's something that is
really divine about them. And it's an interesting way of ending the
story because it's not only a discussion of like mystical beings. If
a way if we were talking about מעשה מרכבה Ma'aseh Merkavah we
should talk more about מלאכי השרת Malachei Hashares directly, not here the
focus is שדים shedim and humans, not the מלאכי השרת. Malachei Hashares.
But I think the interesting thing is again the engaging in מעשה
מרכבה Ma'aseh Merkavah and as we've seen it's sort of the trying
to really rise oneself up to these heights or to bring heaven
down to earth like the story about the angels that came to
hear the talkings of מעשה מרכבה Ma'aseh Merkavah and it deals with
the deep problem of being a physical being and having a spiritual
nature. And so that I think's the point that it ends with
here which is exactly the whole challenge you know about the problematics
of this of מעשה מרכבה. Ma'aseh Merkavah. Okay, so now we go
on. כל המסתכל בארבעה דברים ראוי לו שלא בא לעולם. Kol Hamistakel
Bearba'ah Devarim Raui Lo Shelo Ba Laolam. Anybody who looks at four
things: before, after, up and down, you know, is fit not to
come to the world. Our גרסה Girsa is רצוי, Ratzui, other גרסאות
Girsaos have ראוי Raui which is more familiar to us, essentially it
means the same thing. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, בשלמא
למעלה למטה מה לאחור לחיי, Bishlama Lema'alah Lematah Mah Leachor Lecha'ei, I
understand not investigating what's above or below or or
לאחור Leachor here means in this context we'll see in a minute
clearly means what's what's coming yet to be or the future which
is a funny way of saying it. אלא לפנים, Ela Lefanim, but
in terms of what was in the past, מה דהוה הוה, Mah
Dehava Hava, what was was. Now it's a very strange question, right,
what are the things we're not supposed to be asking and why
does it think it's better to ask what was in the past?
So it seems like as we'll see from the answer that the
issue has to be here about like questioning about the creation about
the world, you know, what exists above the heavens, what exists below
the earth, what is going to be the future of the world,
what was the and then what were the origins of the world
now which means sort of like what exist you know what was
the world before it was the world, how was you know what
was the way in which the world was created? So the גמרא
Gemara seems to feel that somehow asking questions about that would not
be
a somehow being infringing, you know, somehow impugning God's honor in any
way or you know somehow not being... it's not understanding why that's
not respectful of God's honor, you know, I'm trying to understand why
the other things aren't exactly so I don't really get it but
let's see what the answers maybe it'll clarify the question. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי יוחנן בר אלעזר אמר Rabbi Yochanan
bar Elazar amar תובעי tovai רבי יוחנן בר אלעזר Rabbi Yochanan bar
Elazar בוסי bosei משל למלך בשר ודם שאמר לעבדיו בנו לי פלטורין
גדולים. mashal l'melech basar v'dam she'amar l'avdav bnu li paltarin gedolin.
It's like a king says to a servant, build me a huge
castle על האשפה al ha'ashpah on a dung heap. So הולכו holchu
because that was the best available land. הולכו בנו לו, holchu bnu
lo, they went and they built the castle, now everything is beautiful
and they filled in the dung heap, but אין רצונו של המלך
להזכיר שם אשפה. ein ritzono shel hamelech lehazkir shem ashpah. He doesn't
want anybody mentioning, "Oh yeah, that used to be a dung heap."
No, right? A landfill. So presumably God made the world out of
תהו ובהו tohu v'vohu and all this disgusting stuff. So don't talk
about the disgusting stuff; it'll undermine the beauty of the current creation
and therefore it's not respectful of כבוד קונו kvod kono God's honor.
I know, I don't understand it. Believe me, I don't understand what
that's talk about. I don't understand what the issue of לאחור l'achor
and למעלה l'ma'alah and למטה l'matah is either. So hopefully there's no
risk that I'll talk about it, but who knows? Maybe I might
inadvertently talk about it if I don't know what it's talking about.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this: כל שלא חס על
כבוד קונו ראוי לו שלא בא לעולם.
kol shelo chas al kvod
kono rauy lo shelo ba l'olam.
Then it makes another statement which could just be seen as summing
it up, but the גמרא Gemara sees that it's coming to add
another point. Whoever is not protective of God's honor, it's fit that
this person should not come to the world. So what's that coming
to include? מאי היא? mai hi? What does that mean? What else
is included in this? רבי אבא אמר זה המסתכל בקשת. Rabbi Abba
amar zeh hamistakel bakeshet. Somebody who looks at the rainbow. We'll see
in a minute. רבי יוסף אמר זה העובר עבירה בסתר. Rabbi Yosef
amar zeh ha'over aveirah b'seter. That somebody who does a sin in
private. This is very relevant for יום הדין Yom Hadin coming up.
מסתכל בקשת דכתיב, mistakel bakeshet d'chtiv, looking at the rainbow as it
says, כמראה הקשת אשר יהיה בענן ביום הגשם כן מראה הנגה סביב
הוא מראה דמות כבוד השם, k'mareh hakeshet asher yihyeh be'anan b'yom hageshem
ken mareh hanogah saviv hu mareh dmut kvod Hashem, like the vision
of the rainbow that will be in this cloud at the time
of the rain,
so was the vision of the glowing around it.
That is the appearance of the vision of the כבוד השם, kvod
Hashem, the honor of God. So if you look directly at God's
honor, which is somehow seen in the rainbow, the rainbow somehow connects
you to the it's a type of a vision of the כבוד
השם, kvod Hashem, you're not being respectful; you're not supposed to be
looking at it. Now this is obviously bizarre. Like, why? What does
that mean, that that's כבוד השם? kvod Hashem? What's meant by that?
So רבינו חננאל once again says that the problem is that you
think it's כבוד השם, kvod Hashem, not that it is. The problem
that you're not being חס על כבוד קונו, chas al kvod kono,
he says here's his line is, where is it? He says...
I have to find it. Okay, anyway. But anyway, he says, I'll
have to find it, but he says,
what?
Three lines when it gets white.
Thank you. It says, רבי יוחנן בן אלעזר, Rabbi Yochanan ben Eleazar,
it says כל שלא חס על כבוד קונו ראוי לו שלא בא
לעולם. kol shelo chas al kvod kono rauy lo shelo ba l'olam.
המסתכל בקשת האומר. hamistakel bakeshet ha'omer. The problem is if you say
כגון זה דמות השם k'gon zeh dmut Hashem כנאמר כמראה הקשת אשר
יהיה בענן. k'ne'emar k'mareh hakeshet asher yihyeh be'anan. So the problem is
that you actually somehow, some powerful vision and ולא חס v'lo chas
is that you actually will make that comparison, but that actually is
a false comparison. Now I will tell you that in קבלה, Kabbalah,
being מסתכל בקשת mistakel bakeshet is a very big problem and they
really do take this גמרא more literally, that somehow this is some
idea of כבוד השם, kvod Hashem, and part of the problem is,
I hope I'm not going to scandalize anybody, that the קשת keshet
is understood to be, okay, I'm just going to say it, God's
phallus. And if you think about the whole whatever, the whole appearance
of it and a bow shoots arrows that we just mentioned before,
שכבת זרע שיורה כחץ. shichvat zera sheyoreh k'chetz. So if you're looking
at God's nakedness, then you're really not being חס על כבוד קונו.
chas al kvod kono. Okay, I don't know. Okay, it pierces through
the clouds, there's a lot about that in קבלה. Kabbalah. I'm not
making this up, believe me. I couldn't make this up.
In קבלה? Kabbalah? What?
Yeah, I know, but you're not supposed to be מסתכל. mistakel. You
can look at it, but you're not supposed to be מסתכל. mistakel.
Maybe if you just look at it, you're just looking at the
physical thing, but if you're מסתכל, mistakel, then you're looking at it
through a Kabbalistic lens. All right, you're looking at it through a
Kabbalistic lens and you're looking at sort of the mystical aspect of
it and that's deeply problematic. What's that? Gaze, gaze.
Right. I tend to translate the term כבוד השם kvod Hashem as
God's presence. Is that different from what you intend when you say
honor? I find the word honor here abstract.
Yeah, it is abstract, you're right. And כבוד השם kvod Hashem also
like we said before when it says ראוי לי לשמש את כבודי
rauy li l'shamesh et kvodi and כבוד השם kvod Hashem in the
תורה is כבוד השם נראה בענן, kvod Hashem nireh be'anan, it's definitely
some type of a physical manifestation of God's presence. But
חס על כבודו, chas al kvodo, I'm not sure if that has
the same meaning. But okay. Anyway, so let's take a look, let's
just get to the משנה Mishna. at least. So it says like
this,
okay, so that's one explanation. רבי יוסף אמר זה העובר עבירה בסתר.
Rabbi Yosef amar zeh ha'over aveirah b'seter. Somebody who sins in private.
רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, דאמר רבי יצחק, d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, כל העובר
עבירה בסתר כאילו דוחק רגלי שכינה, kol ha'over aveirah b'seter k'ilu dochek
raglei Shechinah, it's like you're pushing out the divine. presence because you're
basically thinking that God doesn't see you if you do it in
private, okay, or you're thinking that the only thing that matters about
sin is that other people see you, you don't care that God
sees you, but either way there's a profound theological problem, right, you
know about doing it in about doing it in private. שנאמר, She'ne'emar,
I mean doing it in public you have חילול השם, Chilul Hashem,
but doing it in private you're being hypocritical and you're just you're
sort of not, you know, it doesn't, you know, it's all about
people, it's not about God or it's denying that God is even
seeing it. שנאמר She'ne'emar as the verse says, כה אמר השם השמים
כסאי והארץ הדום רגלי. Koh amar Hashem hashamayim kisei veha'aretz hadom raglai.
So if God's footstool is the land and you're trying to kick
that out of the land because you're trying to say I can
do it here and God won't, you know, not in God's presence,
so you're pushing out God's, you know, God from the land.
So, איני, Eini, is that really true? ואמר that it's a problem
doing it in private or it's more problematic, ואמר רבי אלעאי הזקן
אם רואה אדם שיצרו מתגבר עליו, Ve'amar Rabbi Illai HaZaken im ro'eh
adam she'yitzro mitgaber alav,
if a person sees that his יצר הרע Yetzer hara is being
victorious over him, he cannot control his lusts, ילך, yelech, which presumably
here specifically of a sexual sense, a connotation but not limited to
that, ילך למקום שאין מכירין אותו, Yelech lemakom she'ein makkirin oto, go
to a place where nobody recognizes him, וילבש שחורים Ve'yilbash shechorim and
dress black clothes, ויתעטף שחורים Ve'yitatef shechorim and black garments, presumably to
disguise oneself, but I'll get back to that in a second, ויעשה
מה שלבו חפץ, Ve'ya'aseh ma shelibo chafetz, and if you have to
sin, at least do it in that context where nobody recognizes you,
okay, that it won't be a חילול השם, Chilul Hashem, okay, so
you see that it's better to do it in a way that
that it's private, that it's not a חילול השם. Chilul Hashem. ואל
יחלל שם שמים בפרהסיא, Ve'al yechalel shem shamayim befarhesya, don't let it
be that you're sinning in in public and people see, you know,
you know that and that obviously carries with it a big problem,
that somebody that you're making a public statement that you don't care
about the fact that you're doing an עבירה, aveira, maybe you're misleading
other people, right, better to do it in this way that no
that it doesn't register for anyone. So the גמרא says, so you
see it's better to do it in private? No, לא קשיא. הא
דמתקיף ליה יצריה הא דלא מתקיף ליה יצריה. Ha de-matikif lei yitzrei
ha de-lo matikif lei yitzrei. The difference is can you control your
desire or not control your desire? If you can't control your desire
and you have to sin, better to do it in a way
that's in private, not in public. But if you can control your
desire, right, and nevertheless you're choosing to sin and you're choosing to
sin in private, so then you are דוחק רגלי השכינה Dochek raglei
ha-Shechina because the alternative is not to sin, and presumably the גמרא
is saying it's, if the alternative is to sin in private or
sin in public, better to sin in public. But if the alternative
is to sin in private or not to sin at all, don't
sin at all, and the part of the problem of private, and
here's the point is, that it's being in private that's allowing me
to sin. If I had to do this in public I would
never do this, right, because but I'm going to allow myself to
do it because nobody is looking and I'm doing it in private.
So that's when you're דוחק רגלי השכינה. Dochek raglei ha-Shechina. It's all
about people, you would never do it in public you're doing it
in private. But if you're going to do it anyway, might as
well do it in public. The problem of course is that how
do you know, and you tell yourself, you know what, I'm going
to do this anyway, might as well do it in private, once
you do it in private, you're giving yourself much more of a
license to continue sinning, right? So this becomes a real difficult problem
and that's why a lot of ראשונים Rishonim were deeply bothered by
this גמרא and they did not read this גמרא כפשוטו. Kipshto. They
said the גמרא that the גמרא is חס ושלום Chas ve'shalom the
גמרא would ever give a license to somebody to sin in private
even as an alternative. And what the גמרא is saying is, if
you go to a place where nobody knows you, so you're feeling
out not at home, you're less, you know, you know, you're not
as likely to to act with a sense of freedom that you
would in your in your hometown and if you're dressing in black
which is clothes of mourning, that's humbling you, and all of this
is supposed to is supposed to prevent you from sinning. So when
it says you'll do what your heart desires, it means and at
that stage your heart won't desire it anymore. So that's a radical
re-read of the גמרא, but because they were just so deeply disturbed
because of the problem. Like yes, it's true, if you gotta sin
anyway, better do it in private, but how can you tell that
to somebody, it becomes a license to do sins in private. And
by the way, רב משה Rav Moshe פיינשטיין Feinstein was asked questions
about somebody said can I wear a, I really have a יצר
הרע Yetzer hara to go to the movies and like the theater,
it's so funny, it wasn't even like I have I remember this
תשובה teshuvah I looked it up before this שיעור shiur that it
was like somebody had had a יצר הרע yetzer hara to go
see pornographic films, this is when you actually had to go to
a movie theater to do that, anyway, but it actually is just
he had a יצר הרע yetzer hara to go to movies, or
he had a יצר הרע yetzer hara or to be at these
places where there was mixed dancing, okay, and should I wear my
כיפה kippah or not wear my כיפה kippah and you know because
to be חילול השם, Chilul Hashem, you know, to wear my כיפה
kippah a פרום Frum Jew is doing this, or not wear my
כיפה, kippah, at the end of the day רב משה Rav Moshe
says like wear your כיפה. kippah. And
part of the problem is once you tell somebody take off your
כיפה, kippah, you're basically giving them a much more of an, yes
you're saving the חילול השם, Chilul Hashem, but you wind up basically
saying, you know, you can get away with this, it's okay, you
don't have to feel, you don't have to feel uncomfortable about what
you're doing and so on. So it's a very sort of, you
know, challenging and problematic type of statement.
But also theologically if you're doing something in private so to speak,
it's as if, you know, God can't see it, right,
it's in private, right, well that's the theological issue. Okay, but let's
just now get, let's just get quickly to the משנה. It says
like this, the גמרא says like this,
דרש רבי יהודה ברבי נחמני מתורגמניה דריש לקיש. darash Rabbi Yehuda b'Rebbe
Nachmani meturgamanai d'Reish Lakish. רבי יהודה ברבי נחמני Rabbi Yehuda b'Rebbe Nachmani
the תורגמן, Turgeman, the translator of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said, כל
המסתכל בג' דברים, kol hamistakel b'gimmel devarim, anybody who peers at three
things, gazes at three things, עיניו כהות, einav kehot, his eyes become
dim. בקשת bakeshet the rainbow, ובנשיא uv'nasi a prince or king, ובכהנים
uv'kohanim and in the כהנים Kohanim when they're דוכנ'ן. duchening. בקשת דכתיב
כמראה הקשת אשר יהיה בענן ביום הגשם הוא מראה דמות כבוד השם,
bakeshet d'ketiv kemarei hakeshet asher yihyeh be'anan b'yom hageshem hu marei demus
kevod Hashem,
like we said before and obviously if you're looking at the glory
of God, you know, and the presence of God or somehow this
glow that's associated with it, that's going to impact your eyesight. ובנשיא
דכתיב ונתת מהודך עליו, uv'nasi d'ketiv venatata mehodcha alav, God
you will give I mean whatever Moshe give from your glory to
Yehoshua, but if that glory ultimately comes from the glory that Moshe
had from being in the presence of God, so, you know, again
a king here has some of a divine glory attached to him,
some type of a, you know, symbol of the of the divinity
of the מלכות Malchus in heaven and therefore that affects your eyesight.
והמסתכל בכהנים בזמן שבית המקדש קיים שהיו עומדים על דוכנן vehamistakel bakohanim
bizman she'Beis HaMikdash kayam shehayu omdim al duchenan when there was a
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Nowadays it's not but in the time of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, I mean we don't look at them because it's the מנהג
minhag not to look at them, but the real הלכה halacha is
when there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and they're doing their and
they're on the platform, מברכין את ישראל mevarachin es Yisrael and giving
the ברכה bracha בשם המפורש b'shem hamiforash and they use God's explicit
name, then the divine presence really rests on their fingers and if
you look at them you are looking at the divine presence. So
all of these three are examples of looking at the divine presence
which is not as bad as, you know, going up to פרדס
Pardes I guess, but still affects your eyesight and dims your eyes.
דרש רבי יהודה ברבי נחמני מתורגמניה דריש לקיש, darash Rabbi Yehuda b'Rebbe
Nachmani meturgamanai d'Reish Lakish, so the same רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the translator of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, you know,
had the gave the following דרשה. drasha. מאי דכתיב, what's meant by
the verse, אל תאמינו ברע, al taaminu b'rei, אל תאמינו ברע, al
taaminu b'rei, do not have trust in a friend, אל תבטחו באלוף
al tivtechu b'aluf and do not put your faith in a אלוף,
aluf, an officer, a dignitary. אם יאמר לך יצר הרע im yomar
lecha yetzer hara which is reading רע rei friend as רע ra
okay evil. If your יצר הרע yetzer hara says to you, חטא
chata sin, here's very appropriate leading into ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, והקדוש
ברוך הוא מוחל, Hakadosh Baruch Hu mochel, yeah go ahead sin, you
know God'll forgive, יום כיפור Yom Kippur's coming up. Okay, so אל
תאמינו, al taaminu, תאמינו taaminu do not believe. So that's אל תאמינו
ברע. al taaminu b'ra. Don't believe in the יצר הרע, yetzer hara,
what the יצר הרע yetzer hara seduces you and tells you to
encourage you to sin. אל תאמינו ברע ואין רע אלא יצר הרע
שנאמר כי יצר לב האדם רע מנעוריו. al taaminu b'ra v'ein ra
ela yetzer hara shene'emar ki yetzer lev ha'adam ra mine'urav. Okay, ואין
אלוף ve'ein aluf and אל תבטחו al tivtechu and you don't believe
the יצר הרע yetzer hara and have trust that God will forgive,
that's the next part, אל תבטחו באלוף. al tivtechu b'aluf. יצר הרע
yetzer hara is telling you, no God'll forgive, don't trust him. God
won't forgive. ואין אלוף אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא שנאמר אלוף נעורי אתה.
ve'ein aluf ela Hakadosh Baruch Hu shene'emar aluf ne'urai atah. Okay, שמא
תאמר מי מעידי בי, shema tomar mi me'idi bi, okay this is
a very powerful ending I think. Oh I'll sin, this gets also
to the idea of sinning in private. I'll sin, who's gonna know?
Okay, מי מעידי בי mi me'idi bi who's gonna testify against me?
אבני ביתו וקורות ביתו של אדם הם מעידים בו. avnei beiso v'koros
beiso shel adam hem me'idim bo. No,
the very bricks of your and your house and the beams in
your house will testify against you. שנאמר כי אבן מקיר תזעק וכפיס
מעץ יעננה, shene'emar ki even mikir tiz'ak v'chaphis mei-eitz ya'anena, the stone
will cry out from the
wall and the piece of wood will, you know, will answer from
the tree or from the beam. וחכמים אומרים v'chachamim omrim and the
sages say נשמתו של אדם מעידה בו, nishmaso shel adam me'idah bo,
your very soul will testify against you. שנאמר משכבת חיקך שמור פתחי
פיך, shene'emar mishkavas cheikecha shemor pischei ficha, from that that that sleeps
in your chest, you know, in your bosom, you should watch the
what you say in your mouth. איזהו דבר ששוכבת בחיקו של אדם,
eizehu davar sheshocheves b'cheiko shel adam, what is the thing that lies
down in the bosom of a man? Okay, הוי אומר זו נשמה,
havei omer zu nishama, it's the soul that's inside of you. ורבי
זריקא אומר שני מלאכי השרת המלוין אותו הם מעידים בו, ve'Rabbi Zreika
omer shenei malachei hashareis hamalvin oso hem me'idim bo, the two heavenly
angels that accompany you will testify against you as the verse says
שנאמר
כי מלאכיו יצוה לך לשמרך בכל דרכיך, shene'emar ki malachav yetzaveh lach
lishmorcha bechol derachecha, the angels will be commanded to watch you, they're
watching you, they're gonna report on you. וחכמים אומרים v'chachamim omrim or
ויש אומרים v'yeish omrim איבריו של אדם מעידים בו, evarav shel adam
me'idim bo, your limbs testify against you, שנאמר ואתם עדי נאם השם
ואני אל, shene'emar v'atem eidai neum Hashem va'ani el, you yourselves are
testimony to your actions. So I just want to say, you know,
all this could be read like somehow metaphysically the limbs are gonna
go up to heaven and say to God here's what this person
did, but I think it's it's worthwhile to take a minute to
think about, you know, the this in real world terms like what
does it mean when we sin, how does it like affect our
very homes and our environments? They themselves, you know, testify like if
somebody's basically I don't know, you know, spending all of his time,
you know, watching TV rather than learning תורה at home, okay not
that whatever ביטול תורה, bitul Torah, not to the biggest sin, but
anyway, but how is it that the home is testifying about what
that person is and what those person's values are and what those
person's activities are? Right? How is it that a person's very, you
know, character is shaped, the נשמה neshama by one's deeds? Right? How
is it that the very limbs of a person, you know, if
you don't work out, you know, your very body
testifies. So I think that you can really read these in very
real ways about how our actions really affect us, our character, our
נשמה, neshama, our environment, our very, our very bodies. Are we training
our mind? Are we, what, how are we using ourselves and the
way in which this stuff can really be our very actions can
reflect on the types of choices that we make. So with that,
I will wish you all a כתיבה וחתימה טובה ksiva v'chasima tova
that this coming year our all of our actions should be for
good and should really reflect for us in all positive ways. שנה
טובה. Shana tova. לשנה טובה. l'shana tova.
We are an hour behind and we have a second section.